<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Oliver Associates</title>
    <link href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca" />
    <updated>2023-06-05T15:37:57-04:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>bo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://www.oliverassociates.ca</id>

    <entry>
        <title>1.01-4: Kelvinator 1934 Cabinet Refrigerator</title>
        <author>
            <name>bo</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/101-4.html"/>
        <id>https://www.oliverassociates.ca/101-4.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/375/1.01-4b.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="01.01: Household Refrigerators "/>

        <updated>2023-06-05T15:37:57-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/375/1.01-4b.jpg" alt="" />
                    HHCC Accession No. 2003.003 HHCC Classification Code: 1.01-4 Description: Household, Four Cubic Cabinet Refrigerator, Kelvinator 1934 1.01 Unitary Refrig and&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/375/1.01-4b.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th><strong>HHCC Accession No. 2003.003</strong></th>
<th><strong>HHCC Classification Code:  1.01-4</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
</table>
<h5 id="description">Description:</h5>
<p>Household, Four Cubic Cabinet Refrigerator, Kelvinator 1934</p>
<hr>
<details>
    <summary><b>Image Gallery (5 Images)</b></summary>
<div class="gallery gallery-wrapper--full"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="6">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/375/gallery/1.01-4b.jpg" data-size="512x768"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/375/gallery/1.01-4b-thumbnail.jpg" alt=""></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/375/gallery/1.01-4c.jpg" data-size="512x768"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/375/gallery/1.01-4c-thumbnail.jpg" alt=""></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/375/gallery/1.01-4d.jpg" data-size="512x768"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/375/gallery/1.01-4d-thumbnail.jpg" alt=""></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/375/gallery/1.01-4.jpg" data-size="512x768"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/375/gallery/1.01-4-thumbnail.jpg" alt=""></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/375/gallery/1.01-4a.jpg" data-size="512x768"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/375/gallery/1.01-4a-thumbnail.jpg" alt=""></a></figure>
</div>
</details>

<h5 id="group">Group:</h5>
<p>1.01 Unitary Refrig and A/C Equipment and Systems - Household Cabinet Refrigerators</p>
<h5 id="make">Make:</h5>
<p>Kelvinator</p>
<h5 id="manufacturer">Manufacturer:</h5>
<p>Kelvinator of Canada, London Ontario</p>
<h5 id="model">Model:</h5>
<p>N, See Note #1</p>
<h5 id="serial-no">Serial No.:</h5>
<p>See Note #1</p>
<h5 id="size">Size:</h5>
<p>24x23x51’</p>
<h5 id="weight">Weight:</h5>
<p>250 lbs.</p>
<h5 id="circa">Circa:</h5>
<p>1934</p>
<h5 id="rating">Rating:</h5>
<p>Rare, Exhibit quality</p>
<h5 id="patent-datenumber">Patent Date/Number:</h5>
<h5 id="provenance">Provenance:</h5>
<p>From York County (York Region) Ontario, once a rich agricultural hinterlands, attracting early settlement in the last years of the 18th century. Located on the north slopes of the Oak Ridges Moraine, within 20 miles of Toronto, the County would also attract early ex-urban development, to be come a wealthy market place for the emerging household and consumer technologies of the early and mid 20th century. </p>
<p>This artifact was discovered in the 1950’s in the used stock of T. H. Oliver, Refrigeration and Electric Sales and Service, Aurora, Ontario, an early worker in the field of agricultural, industrial and consumer technology.</p>
<h5 id="type-and-design">Type and Design:</h5>
<p>Operating system, compression refrigeration type, theoretical Carnot cycle. 
Design: unitary design and construction with insulated refrigerated cabinet, evaporator and expansion valve, and self-contained refrigerant condensing unit, electric motor driven. </p>
<p>Refrigerating Unit (Condensing Unit): Type: Self-contained condensing unit with belt driven compressor, single-phase electric motor, and air-cooled condenser. Design: Non-hermetic design, steel base with coil spring mounting, </p>
<p>Evaporator: Original Kelvinator porcelain on steel, high side float evaporator Part No. 13561 upgraded with Kelvinator stainless steel ‘modernizing’ evaporator Part No. 122628 (See THOC Ref.. 1.6, P23).</p>
<h5 id="construction">Construction:</h5>
<h5 id="material">Material:</h5>
<h5 id="special-features">Special Features:</h5>
<h5 id="accessories">Accessories:</h5>
<h5 id="capacities">Capacities:</h5>
<h5 id="performance-characteristics">Performance Characteristics:</h5>
<h5 id="operation">Operation:</h5>
<h5 id="control-and-regulation">Control and Regulation:</h5>
<h5 id="targeted-market-segment">Targeted Market Segment:</h5>
<h5 id="consumer-acceptance">Consumer Acceptance:</h5>
<h5 id="merchandising">Merchandising:</h5>
<h5 id="market-price">Market Price:</h5>
<h5 id="technological-significance">Technological Significance:</h5>
<p>Unitary Refrigeration Equipment: The idea of a unitary piece of refrigeration or air conditioning equipment was a significant one in its own right, one that had to wait its time. The scientists, engineers and inventors in the early years of the 20th century were intrigued and obsessed with the power of the technology and of its possible market potential. What they saw was the newly discovered principles of physics and heat engines - following, for example, the early works of Carnot, Faraday, Kelvin, and the later work of Perkins, Larsen and Carrier, to name a few. </p>
<p>They understood the promise of the technology for the public good, not to say its consumer sales potential. Early engineering work advanced on a multiple fronts with development of compressors, heat exchangers, valves and piping variously strung together in configurations that would be found to work, but only after much experimentation.</p>
<p>The arrival of unitary equipment, all those parts organised into a single whole, a single unit of construction, a ‘black box’, that could be offered to the consumer market was a significant technological and cultural event. Technologically the refrigerator would need to be seen to be safe, reliable, maintainable and useful. As well, in order to attract the development capital needed, it must be seen as potentially saleable and affordable, contributing to life’s needs and desires. Its socio- cultural and economic significance was marked, for it would change much. As Canadians we would quickly come enjoy potentially healthier lives, expect new levels of comfort and convenience, with a broader, safer, more diverse and enjoyable diet. </p>
<p>Canadians would quickly come to think of their day differently, for the day would be defined and punctuated in different ways than ever before, as a result of the introduction of modern, electric, household appliances, of which refrigerators, freezers and room air conditioners would be a central part, by the mid 20th century </p>
<p>J. M Larsen produced a manually operated household refrigerator of sorts in 1913, but it was not until 1918 that the Kelvinator Company marketed the first automatic, unitary refrigerator for the home. In that year, it is reported to have sold sixty-seven machines. (See Note 1) The historic artifacts in Group 1.00, Unitary Equipment, including significant samplings the early work of Kelvinator of Canada, provide a rare view of the evolution of unitary refrigeration and air conditioning applications, as they evolved in Canada in the first half of the 20th century. </p>
<p>For those formative years, the artifacts in this Group, 1.00,  are typical of the offerings of the Canadian refrigeration and air conditioning industry. They personified the applications found in the homes, farms and commercial premises of the period for, those that could afford life’s new amenities of comfort, convenience and privilege. </p>
<p>This Specimen: This machine symbolises a unique period in the development of the industry. It was part of the first growth period of the household refrigerator as a mass consumer good, moving beyond the embryonic years and the exclusive appeal to the elite market ‘ once believed to be the only market. A second significant growth period would follow the pent up consumer demand of the late 1940’s a consequence of the Second World War. At that time, it was a first-time buyer’s market without trade-ins to be contended with. But for now the industry was targeting the first time buyer of modest means. It was a ‘refrigerator in every kitchen marketing’ ‘ following the lead of ther auto industry.</p>
<h5 id="industrial-significance">Industrial Significance:</h5>
<p>By the early 1930’s it was realized that the much hoped for growth period of the industry, like that of the automobile industry, would come not from the manufacture and sale of high-end products, but also through the production of much more popularly affordable machines for middle class consumption, ones configured much better for the kitchens of the nation. - This refrigerator represents the early 1930’s market response to ‘the refrigerator in every kitchen’ movement, paralleling the ‘automobile in every garage’ movement of the times. It was originally priced at a low of $216.00 (See Ref. 1.2, Section 2, Form, C4916AA, price list dated Feb. 1 1935), for a replacement price in 1996 dollars of $2,650 - yet still a very sizeable investment for most households.</p>
<h5 id="socio-economic-significance">Socio-economic Significance:</h5>
<p>It was a period of rapid technological change, with new materials, manufacturing methods, as well as new innovations in the design and development of compressors, evaporator and condensing systems, flow controls and electric motors all contributing to quieter, more efficient and better performing machines. </p>
<p>It was also a period in which the economics and ethics of the times, as well as engineering practices in system design and construction, readily supported technological change with out creating undue obsolescence. The ‘open systems’ of the early 1930’s allowed for changes to new refrigerants as they were introduced ( This machine was converted from original S02 to CH3CL to F12), to new style evaporators and flow control systems, as well as to new quieter, and efficient electric motors.</p>
<p>Kelvinator promoted its ‘modernization and revamp program’ (See Ref. 1.8, Bulletin No. 35-108. Sept. 1935) providing the engineering support needed for its dealers and the service industry. As a result any of these sturdy (400 lb.) machines were in operation well into the 1950’s, some, such as this specimen, surviving well into the 1960’s, having gone through many retrofits, lives and owners.</p>
<h5 id="socio-cultural-significance">Socio-cultural Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="donor">Donor:</h5>
<p>G. Leslie Oliver, The T. H. Oliver HVACR Collection</p>
<h5 id="hhcc-storage-location">HHCC Storage Location:</h5>
<h5 id="tracking">Tracking:</h5>
<h5 id="bibliographic-references">Bibliographic References:</h5>
<p>ThumbNail Profile see THOC Ref doc OC9908B</p>
<h5 id="notes">Notes:</h5>
<p>Note #1: Cabinet model N, Part No, 25471, serial 0101534, see Ref 1.7, form 1670, Nov.1934; Ref 1.3, P. 73 for specifications 
Condensing Unit Model A9116, Serial 33805</p>
<h5 id="related-reports">Related Reports:</h5>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>1.02-1: Frigidaire 1955 Through-The-Window, Room Air Conditioner</title>
        <author>
            <name>bo</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/1.02-1.html"/>
        <id>https://www.oliverassociates.ca/1.02-1.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/376/1.02-1.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="01.02: Household Air Conditioners "/>

        <updated>2023-05-15T14:11:34-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/376/1.02-1.jpg" alt="" />
                    HHCC Accession No. 2003.006 HHCC Classification Code: 1.02-1 Description: Household, Through-the-Window, Room Air Conditioner, Frigidaire, 1956 1.02 Unitary Refrig. and&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/376/1.02-1.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th><strong>HHCC Accession No. 2003.006</strong></th>
<th><strong>HHCC Classification Code:  1.02-1</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
</table>
<h5 id="description">Description:</h5>
<p>Household, Through-the-Window, Room Air Conditioner, Frigidaire, 1956</p>
<hr>
<h5 id="group">Group:</h5>
<p>1.02 Unitary Refrig. and A/C Equipment and Systems - Household Air Conditioners</p>
<h5 id="make">Make:</h5>
<p>Frigidaire</p>
<h5 id="manufacturer">Manufacturer:</h5>
<p>Frigidaire Products Canada Ltd, Scarborough, Ont</p>
<h5 id="model">Model:</h5>
<p>Super 33</p>
<h5 id="serial-no">Serial No.:</h5>
<p>50Y2859</p>
<h5 id="size">Size:</h5>
<p>15x 36x 13.5’</p>
<h5 id="weight">Weight:</h5>
<p>115 lbs</p>
<h5 id="circa">Circa:</h5>
<p>1955</p>
<h5 id="rating">Rating:</h5>
<p>Exhibit Quality, excellent example of the gendre, fully operational, new and unused</p>
<h5 id="patent-datenumber">Patent Date/Number:</h5>
<h5 id="provenance">Provenance:</h5>
<p>From York County (York Region) Ontario, once a rich agricultural hinterlands, attracting early settlement in the last years of the 18th century. Located on the north slopes of the Oak Ridges Moraine, within 20 miles of Toronto, the County would also attract early ex-urban development, to be come a wealthy market place for the emerging household and consumer technologies of the early and mid 20th century. </p>
<p>This artifact was discovered in the 1950’s in the used stock of T. H. Oliver, Refrigeration and Electric Sales and Service, Aurora, Ontario, an early worker in the field of agricultural, industrial and consumer technology.</p>
<h5 id="type-and-design">Type and Design:</h5>
<p>A household, unitary, room air conditioner designed for through the window applications, in which the heat is rejected to the exterior of the home by means of a forced air condenser. The air conditioner operating system employs the compression refrigeration cycle operating on a theoretical Carnot cycle</p>
<h5 id="construction">Construction:</h5>
<h5 id="material">Material:</h5>
<h5 id="special-features">Special Features:</h5>
<p>Automatic temperature control, Outside fresh air damper Air filter Complete, original installation kit</p>
<h5 id="accessories">Accessories:</h5>
<p>:
Full text sales, application and engineering design manuals included.</p>
<h5 id="capacities">Capacities:</h5>
<p>This air conditioner, 1/3 HP in capacity, was minimum for useful household cooling. Designed for a small bedroom, it would provide the taste for the latest appliance of the times, helping to build market demand. It was in the 1950’s that the leading principle of consumer economics began to be popularly recognised ‘  i.e., demand is generated by the means by which it is satisfied, consumption.</p>
<h5 id="performance-characteristics">Performance Characteristics:</h5>
<h5 id="operation">Operation:</h5>
<h5 id="control-and-regulation">Control and Regulation:</h5>
<h5 id="targeted-market-segment">Targeted Market Segment:</h5>
<p>The household air conditioning business was still in its infancy in Canada in 1955, with many predictions that it would go nowhere. It would be difficult to have anticipated that by the end of the century few homes in the urban areas of southern Ontario would be built without central summer air conditioning. </p>
<p>The window air conditioner was thus a harbinger, an early market indicator of what was to come. The single room, through the window air conditioner, was an essential part of the first wave of air conditioning engineering for the home, allowing the industry to develop the equipment design, application protocols and standards and test the interest of the market place for what might follow.</p>
<h5 id="consumer-acceptance">Consumer Acceptance:</h5>
<h5 id="merchandising">Merchandising:</h5>
<h5 id="market-price">Market Price:</h5>
<h5 id="technological-significance">Technological Significance:</h5>
<p>Unitary Refrigeration Equipment: The idea of a unitary piece of refrigeration or air conditioning equipment was a significant one in its own right, one that had to wait its time. The scientists, engineers and inventors in the early years of the 20th century were intrigued and obsessed with the power of the technology and of its possible market potential. What they saw was the newly discovered principles of physics and heat engines - following, for example, the early works of Carnot, Faraday, Kelvin, and the later work of Perkins, Larsen and Carrier, to name a few. </p>
<p>They understood the promise of the technology for the public good, not to say its consumer sales potential. Early engineering work advanced on a multiple fronts with development of compressors, heat exchangers, valves and piping variously strung together in configurations that would be found to work, but only after much experimentation.</p>
<p>The arrival of unitary equipment, all those parts organised into a single whole, a single unit of construction, a ‘black box’, that could be offered to the consumer market was a significant technological and cultural event. Technologically the refrigerator would need to be seen to be safe, reliable, maintainable and useful. As well, in order to attract the development capital needed, it must be seen as potentially saleable and affordable, contributing to life’s needs and desires. Its socio- cultural and economic significance was marked, for it would change much. As Canadians we would quickly come enjoy potentially healthier lives, expect new levels of comfort and convenience, with a broader, safer, more diverse and enjoyable diet. </p>
<p>Canadians would quickly come to think of their day differently, for the day would be defined and punctuated in different ways than ever before, as a result of the introduction of modern, electric, household appliances, of which refrigerators, freezers and room air conditioners would be a central part, by the mid 20th century </p>
<p>J. M Larsen produced a manually operated household refrigerator of sorts in 1913, but it was not until 1918 that the Kelvinator Company marketed the first automatic, unitary refrigerator for the home. In that year, it is reported to have sold sixty-seven machines. (See Note 1) The historic artifacts in Group 1.00, Unitary Equipment, including significant samplings the early work of Kelvinator of Canada, provide a rare view of the evolution of unitary refrigeration and air conditioning applications, as they evolved in Canada in the first half of the 20th century. </p>
<p>For those formative years, the artifacts in this Group, 1.00, are typical of the offerings of the Canadian refrigeration and air conditioning industry. They personified the applications found in the homes, farms and commercial premises of the period for, those that could afford life’s new amenities of comfort, convenience and privilege. </p>
<p>This Specimen stands as a marker of the embryonic years of household air conditioning in Canada. While vastly under powered, by the standards that would follow, it was for most urban dwellers affordable and a significant market opener.</p>
<h5 id="industrial-significance">Industrial Significance:</h5>
<p>The development of high heat transfer, capacity compressors, condensers, evaporators and flow control devices, at a price that home owners were likely to find affordable, would be a major challenge and success story for the refrigeration industry in the early years of home air conditioning. The industry would quickly adapting what had been learned in the design of reliable hermetic compressors and coiling for the food industry to high heat transfer systems required for household air conditioning applications.</p>
<p>Suddenly the refrigeration and air conditioning industry expanded dramatically with a number of new non-traditional players designing, manufacturing and marketing equipment for household and commercial applications. In the face of increasing competition from manufactures with massive engineering and production facilities, many of the traditional suppliers to the refrigeration field would quickly fade from their earlier position of market leadership, including Kelvinator and Frigidaire.</p>
<h5 id="socio-economic-significance">Socio-economic Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="socio-cultural-significance">Socio-cultural Significance:</h5>
<p>The room air conditioner, window mounted, stands as a significant icon of social and cultural change in 20th century life in Canada. Starting in the mid 1950’s, it would soon change the expectations of Canadians of the comfort conditions technology had now made available for all those who valued it and could afford the comfort of summer air conditioning.</p>
<h5 id="donor">Donor:</h5>
<p>G. Leslie Oliver, The T. H. Oliver HVACR Collection</p>
<h5 id="hhcc-storage-location">HHCC Storage Location:</h5>
<h5 id="tracking">Tracking:</h5>
<h5 id="bibliographic-references">Bibliographic References:</h5>
<p>Frigidaire Air Conditioning Product Memos 1956 [manual]</p>
<h5 id="notes">Notes:</h5>
<h5 id="related-reports">Related Reports:</h5>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>1.03-1: Kelvinator 1928 Double Door, Cabinet Refrigerator</title>
        <author>
            <name>bo</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/1.03-1.html"/>
        <id>https://www.oliverassociates.ca/1.03-1.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/377/1.03-1.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="01.03: Commercial Refrigerating Equipment "/>

        <updated>2023-05-15T14:11:34-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/377/1.03-1.jpg" alt="" />
                    HHCC Accession No. 2003.008 HHCC Classification Code: 1.03-1 Description: Nine and One Half Cubic Foot, Double door, Cabinet Refrigerator, Frigidaire,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/377/1.03-1.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th><strong>HHCC Accession No. 2003.008</strong></th>
<th><strong>HHCC Classification Code:  1.03-1</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
</table>
<h5 id="description">Description:</h5>
<p>Nine and One Half Cubic Foot, Double door, Cabinet Refrigerator, Frigidaire, 1926</p>
<hr>
<details>
    <summary><b>Image Gallery (2 Images)</b></summary>
<div class="gallery gallery-wrapper--full"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="6">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/377/gallery/1.03-1.jpg" data-size="512x768"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/377/gallery/1.03-1-thumbnail.jpg" alt=""></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/377/gallery/1.03-1a.jpg" data-size="512x768"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/377/gallery/1.03-1a-thumbnail.jpg" alt=""></a></figure>
</div>
</details>

<h5 id="group">Group:</h5>
<p>1.03 Unitary Refrig and A/C Equipment and Systems - Commercial Refrigerating Equipment</p>
<h5 id="make">Make:</h5>
<p>Kelvinator</p>
<h5 id="manufacturer">Manufacturer:</h5>
<p>Kelvinator of Canada, London Ont.</p>
<h5 id="model">Model:</h5>
<p>233</p>
<h5 id="serial-no">Serial No.:</h5>
<p>1700</p>
<h5 id="size">Size:</h5>
<p>41x 25x 70”h</p>
<h5 id="weight">Weight:</h5>
<p>360 lls</p>
<h5 id="circa">Circa:</h5>
<p>1928</p>
<h5 id="rating">Rating:</h5>
<p>Exhibit Quality, Rare example of the genre in white porcelain exterior finish ,</p>
<h5 id="patent-datenumber">Patent Date/Number:</h5>
<p>Sept 1910 to May 1921</p>
<h5 id="provenance">Provenance:</h5>
<p>From York County (York Region) Ontario, once a rich agricultural hinterlands, attracting early settlement in the last years of the 18th century. Located on the north slopes of the Oak Ridges Moraine, within 20 miles of Toronto, the County would also attract early ex-urban development, to be come a wealthy market place for the emerging household and consumer technologies of the early and mid 20th century. </p>
<p>This artifact was discovered in the 1950’s in the used stock of T. H. Oliver, Refrigeration and Electric Sales and Service, Aurora, Ontario, an early worker in the field of agricultural, industrial and consumer technology.</p>
<h5 id="type-and-design">Type and Design:</h5>
<p>Unitary design and construction with natural cork insulated refrigerated cabinet, self-contained refrigerant condensing unit, 1/4 HP electric motor. 
Refrigerating Unit (Condensing Unit): Type: Operating system type, compression refrigeration type, theoretical Carnot cycle; 
Self-contained condensing unit with belts driven compressor, single-phase electric motor, and air-cooled condenser. Non-hermetic design, steel base with coil spring mounting/steel legs,</p>
<h5 id="construction">Construction:</h5>
<p>Wooden frame construction, 2” natural Cork insulation with expressed, bolted, applied, porcelain steel panels, with curved, cast aluminium, archetectural corners in Art Deco style of the period</p>
<h5 id="material">Material:</h5>
<h5 id="special-features">Special Features:</h5>
<p>Four heavy galvanised steel wire shelves; evaporator baffles (evaporator not included), early refrigerator lift latches in pristine condition</p>
<h5 id="accessories">Accessories:</h5>
<p>: 
Original sales, service and engineering manuals</p>
<h5 id="capacities">Capacities:</h5>
<p>120 volts, 1/4 HP, 3.5 amps</p>
<h5 id="performance-characteristics">Performance Characteristics:</h5>
<h5 id="operation">Operation:</h5>
<h5 id="control-and-regulation">Control and Regulation:</h5>
<h5 id="targeted-market-segment">Targeted Market Segment:</h5>
<p>In addition to its market potential for small grocery stores of the times, a  nine cubic foot refrigerator with ample icemaker was an elite piece of household equipment for the early 1930’s. It was marketed for the homes of the wealthy, a carefully targeted segment of the population  (See also Report 009)</p>
<h5 id="consumer-acceptance">Consumer Acceptance:</h5>
<h5 id="merchandising">Merchandising:</h5>
<h5 id="market-price">Market Price:</h5>
<h5 id="technological-significance">Technological Significance:</h5>
<p>Unitary Refrigeration Equipment: The idea of a unitary piece of refrigeration or air conditioning equipment was a significant one in its own right, one that had to wait its time. The scientists, engineers and inventors in the early years of the 20th century were intrigued and obsessed with the power of the technology and of its possible market potential. What they saw was the newly discovered principles of physics and heat engines - following, for example, the early works of Carnot, Faraday, Kelvin, and the later work of Perkins, Larsen and Carrier, to name a few. </p>
<p>They understood the promise of the technology for the public good, not to say its consumer sales potential. Early engineering work advanced on a multiple fronts with development of compressors, heat exchangers, valves and piping variously strung together in configurations that would be found to work, but only after much experimentation.</p>
<p>The arrival of unitary equipment, all those parts organised into a single whole, a single unit of construction, a ‘black box’, that could be offered to the consumer market was a significant technological and cultural event. Technologically the refrigerator would need to be seen to be safe, reliable, maintainable and useful. As well, in order to attract the development capital needed, it must be seen as potentially saleable and affordable, contributing to life’s needs and desires. Its socio- cultural and economic significance was marked, for it would change much. As Canadians we would quickly come enjoy potentially healthier lives, expect new levels of comfort and convenience, with a broader, safer, more diverse and enjoyable diet. </p>
<p>As a result, Canadians would quickly come to think of their day differently, for the day would be defined and punctuated in different ways than ever before, as a result of the introduction of modern, electric, household appliances, of which refrigerators, freezers and room air conditioners would be a central part, by the mid 20th century </p>
<p>J. M Larsen produced a manually operated household refrigerator of sorts in 1913, but it was not until 1918 that the Kelvinator Company marketed the first automatic, unitary refrigerator for the home. In that year, it is reported to have sold sixty-seven machines. (See Note 1) The historic artifacts in Group 1.00, Unitary Equipment, including significant samplings the early work of Kelvinator of Canada, provide a rare view of the evolution of unitary refrigeration and air conditioning applications, as they evolved in Canada in the first half of the 20th century. </p>
<p>For those formative years, the artifacts in this Group, 1.00, are typical of the offerings of the Canadian refrigeration and air conditioning industry. They personified the applications found in the homes, farms and commercial premises of the period for, those that could afford life’s new amenities of comfort, convenience and privilege. </p>
<p>The Significance of this Specimen: The significant contribution of refrigerators, represented by this specimen lies in the market for the technology opened up for larger refrigerators, which would grace the kitchens of wealthy estates throughout the 1930’s, as well as being found in a new generation of food retailers, the family run,”mumma and papa” store of the pre WW II era.</p>
<h5 id="industrial-significance">Industrial Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="socio-economic-significance">Socio-economic Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="socio-cultural-significance">Socio-cultural Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="donor">Donor:</h5>
<p>G. Leslie Oliver, The T. H. Oliver HVACR Collection</p>
<h5 id="hhcc-storage-location">HHCC Storage Location:</h5>
<h5 id="tracking">Tracking:</h5>
<h5 id="bibliographic-references">Bibliographic References:</h5>
<p>Kelvinator Service Manual, 1928</p>
<h5 id="notes">Notes:</h5>
<h5 id="related-reports">Related Reports:</h5>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>1.02-2: GE 1959 Through-The-Wall, Room, Air Conditioner</title>
        <author>
            <name>bo</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/1.02-2.html"/>
        <id>https://www.oliverassociates.ca/1.02-2.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/378/1.02-2.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="01.02: Household Air Conditioners "/>

        <updated>2023-05-15T14:11:34-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/378/1.02-2.jpg" alt="" />
                    HHCC Accession No. 2003.007 HHCC Classification Code: 1.02-2 Description: Household, Through-the-Wall, Room, Air Conditioner, General Electric, 1959 1.02 Unitary Refrig.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/378/1.02-2.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th><strong>HHCC Accession No. 2003.007</strong></th>
<th><strong>HHCC Classification Code:  1.02-2</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
</table>
<h5 id="description">Description:</h5>
<p>Household, Through-the-Wall, Room, Air Conditioner, General Electric, 1959</p>
<hr>
<h5 id="group">Group:</h5>
<p>1.02 Unitary Refrig. and A/C Equipment and Systems - Household Air Conditioners</p>
<h5 id="make">Make:</h5>
<p>General Electric</p>
<h5 id="manufacturer">Manufacturer:</h5>
<p>GE, Louisville USA</p>
<h5 id="model">Model:</h5>
<p>1R32NA</p>
<h5 id="serial-no">Serial No.:</h5>
<p>SN2-01292</p>
<h5 id="size">Size:</h5>
<p>25x 16 1/2x 21’</p>
<h5 id="weight">Weight:</h5>
<h5 id="circa">Circa:</h5>
<p>1959</p>
<h5 id="rating">Rating:</h5>
<p>Exhibit Quality, excellent example of the genre, new , fully operational equipment with original price tag</p>
<h5 id="patent-datenumber">Patent Date/Number:</h5>
<h5 id="provenance">Provenance:</h5>
<p>From York County (York Region) Ontario, once a rich agricultural hinterlands, attracting early settlement in the last years of the 18th century. Located on the north slopes of the Oak Ridges Moraine, within 20 miles of Toronto, the County would also attract early ex-urban development, to be come a wealthy market place for the emerging household and consumer technologies of the early and mid 20th century. </p>
<p>This artifact was discovered in the 1960’s in the stock of T. H. Oliver, Refrigeration and Electric Sales and Service, Aurora, Ontario, an early worker in the field of agricultural, industrial and consumer technology.</p>
<h5 id="type-and-design">Type and Design:</h5>
<p>A household, unitary, room air conditioner designed for through-the-wall, or through-the-window applications, in which the heat is rejected to the exterior of the home by means of a forced air condenser. The air conditioner operating system employs the compression refrigeration cycle operating on a theoretical Carnot cycle.</p>
<h5 id="construction">Construction:</h5>
<h5 id="material">Material:</h5>
<h5 id="special-features">Special Features:</h5>
<p>Automatic temperature control, out-side air damper, air filter air freshning cartridge Unused equipment with original price tag and original owners manual</p>
<h5 id="accessories">Accessories:</h5>
<p>:</p>
<h5 id="capacities">Capacities:</h5>
<p>120Volts, 6.5 Amps, 60 cycle, 1/2 HP,</p>
<h5 id="performance-characteristics">Performance Characteristics:</h5>
<h5 id="operation">Operation:</h5>
<h5 id="control-and-regulation">Control and Regulation:</h5>
<p>Automatic temperature control</p>
<h5 id="targeted-market-segment">Targeted Market Segment:</h5>
<p>The household, summer air conditioning market developed through the 1960-70’s much more rapidly in southern Ontario than many anticipated helped by the buoyant economy of the post WWII years and the culture of social change and consumerism that was evident. </p>
<p>For many householders and small commercial applications, the through-the-wall room air conditioner was the next step, in adaptation to central, summer, comfort cooling. Many manufactures, such as GE made one model adaptable for both through-the-window and wall applications.</p>
<h5 id="consumer-acceptance">Consumer Acceptance:</h5>
<h5 id="merchandising">Merchandising:</h5>
<p>The market competition for room air conditioners was fierce, with a small select market to draw on manufacturers were looking to features to promote their products and increase market share, many of little real functional value to the owner. A throwaway capsule it was quickly exhausted. The air freshener capsule provided by GE was such a sales gimmick.</p>
<h5 id="market-price">Market Price:</h5>
<p>Original prise tag shows marked down price of $179.50, well below list prices for the period.</p>
<h5 id="technological-significance">Technological Significance:</h5>
<p>Unitary Refrigeration Equipment: The idea of a unitary piece of refrigeration or air conditioning equipment was a significant one in its own right, one that had to wait its time. The scientists, engineers and inventors in the early years of the 20th century were intrigued and obsessed with the power of the technology and of its possible market potential. What they saw was the newly discovered principles of physics and heat engines - following, for example, the early works of Carnot, Faraday, Kelvin, and the later work of Perkins, Larsen and Carrier, to name a few. </p>
<p>They understood the promise of the technology for the public good, not to say its consumer sales potential. Early engineering work advanced on a multiple fronts with development of compressors, heat exchangers, valves and piping variously strung together in configurations that would be found to work, but only after much experimentation.</p>
<p>The arrival of unitary equipment, all those parts organised into a single whole, a single unit of construction, a ‘black box’, that could be offered to the consumer market was a significant technological and cultural event. Technologically the refrigerator would need to be seen to be safe, reliable, maintainable and useful. As well, in order to attract the development capital needed, it must be seen as potentially saleable and affordable, contributing to life’s needs and desires. Its socio- cultural and economic significance was marked, for it would change much. As Canadians we would quickly come enjoy potentially healthier lives, expect new levels of comfort and convenience, with a broader, safer, more diverse and enjoyable diet. </p>
<p>As a result, Canadians would quickly come to think of their day differently, for the day would be defined and punctuated in different ways than ever before, as a result of the introduction of modern, electric, household appliances, of which refrigerators, freezers and room air conditioners would be a central part, by the mid 20th century </p>
<p>J. M Larsen produced a manually operated household refrigerator of sorts in 1913, but it was not until 1918 that the Kelvinator Company marketed the first automatic, unitary refrigerator for the home. In that year, it is reported to have sold sixty-seven machines. (See Note 1) The historic artifacts in Group 1.00, Unitary Equipment, including significant samplings the early work of Kelvinator of Canada, provide a rare view of the evolution of unitary refrigeration and air conditioning applications, as they evolved in Canada in the first half of the 20th century. </p>
<p>For those formative years, the artifacts in this Group, 1.00, are typical of the offerings of the Canadian refrigeration and air conditioning industry. They personified the applications found in the homes, farms and commercial premises of the period for, those that could afford life’s new amenities of comfort, convenience and privilege. </p>
<p>The Significance of this Specimen rests in its special transitional status as a “sandwich technology’, between the window, room air conditioner and central summer cooling for the Canadian home, which would soon follow for all those who could afford it.</p>
<h5 id="industrial-significance">Industrial Significance:</h5>
<p>Beautifully engineered and crafted this machine stands as a model of the refrigeration engineering know-how of the period, as well as the sophisticated production engineering that industry giants, with massive economic resources, such as GE, could bring to the field.</p>
<h5 id="socio-economic-significance">Socio-economic Significance:</h5>
<p>See Report 006</p>
<h5 id="socio-cultural-significance">Socio-cultural Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="donor">Donor:</h5>
<p>G. Leslie Oliver, The T. H. Oliver HVACR Collection</p>
<h5 id="hhcc-storage-location">HHCC Storage Location:</h5>
<h5 id="tracking">Tracking:</h5>
<h5 id="bibliographic-references">Bibliographic References:</h5>
<h5 id="notes">Notes:</h5>
<h5 id="related-reports">Related Reports:</h5>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>2.01-4: Frigidaire 1926 Two Tray, Icemaker with Low-Side Float</title>
        <author>
            <name>bo</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/2.01-4.html"/>
        <id>https://www.oliverassociates.ca/2.01-4.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/379/2.01-4.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="02.01: Household Evaporators"/>

        <updated>2023-05-15T14:11:34-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/379/2.01-4.jpg" alt="" />
                    HHCC Accession No. 2003.013 HHCC Classification Code: 2.01-4 Description: Two tray, icemaker evaporator with low-side float; cooling unit for household&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/379/2.01-4.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th><strong>HHCC Accession No. 2003.013</strong></th>
<th><strong>HHCC Classification Code:  2.01-4</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
</table>
<h5 id="description">Description:</h5>
<p>Two tray, icemaker evaporator with low-side float; cooling unit for household cabinet refrigerator. Fabricated in tinned copper plate with deep draw brass header , brass flanged float valve calibrated for use on liquid sulphur dioxide. It was temperamental and came previously close to not working at all ‘ and would not have, except for the precision and dedication shown in engineering, materials development and manufacture, as well as in the knowledge and skill of the service man who had to attend to it needs on a regular basis, Frigidaire,1926 [Rev 080320]</p>
<hr>
<h5 id="group">Group:</h5>
<p>2.01 Refrigerating and Air Conditioning Evaporators - Household</p>
<h5 id="make">Make:</h5>
<p>Frigidaire</p>
<h5 id="manufacturer">Manufacturer:</h5>
<p>Frigidaire, USA</p>
<h5 id="model">Model:</h5>
<p>1TF</p>
<h5 id="serial-no">Serial No.:</h5>
<p>Float valve # 9</p>
<h5 id="size">Size:</h5>
<p>9x 11x 13’</p>
<h5 id="weight">Weight:</h5>
<p>20 lbs</p>
<h5 id="circa">Circa:</h5>
<p>1926</p>
<h5 id="rating">Rating:</h5>
<p>Exhibit Quality, very early, Rare</p>
<h5 id="patent-datenumber">Patent Date/Number:</h5>
<h5 id="provenance">Provenance:</h5>
<p>From York County (York Region) Ontario, once a rich agricultural hinterlands, attracting early settlement in the last years of the 18th century. Located on the north slopes of the Oak Ridges Moraine, within 20 miles of Toronto, the County would also attract early ex-urban development, to be come a wealthy market place for the emerging household and consumer technologies of the early and mid 20th century. </p>
<p>This artifact was discovered in the 1950’s in the used stock of T. H. Oliver, Refrigeration and Electric Sales and Service, Aurora, Ontario, an early worker in the field of agricultural, industrial and consumer technology.</p>
<h5 id="type-and-design">Type and Design:</h5>
<p>Flooded evaporator in tinned, heavy copper plate, with brass float chamber, brass, flange mounted float assembly, calibrated for S02 refrigerant, 9 pass 1/2  copper coil distributing tubes, with right and left side plate fins. .Equipped with 2 very  crude, brake formed, heavy copper, tinned sheet stock, Two ice cube trays with one removable ice cube grid, 18 cubes</p>
<h5 id="construction">Construction:</h5>
<h5 id="material">Material:</h5>
<h5 id="special-features">Special Features:</h5>
<h5 id="accessories">Accessories:</h5>
<p>Two ice cube trays, one shallow, one deep for frozen food Liquid and suction shut off valves not included</p>
<h5 id="capacities">Capacities:</h5>
<p>Frigidaire rated this evaporator for 2 trays of ice cubes, 18 per tray for 51 lbs of ice per filling</p>
<h5 id="performance-characteristics">Performance Characteristics:</h5>
<h5 id="operation">Operation:</h5>
<p>Requires 5 lbs of So2 to fully flood the coil, with a total systems charge of possibly double that - enough refrigerant gas to make a leak very unpleasant in the household.</p>
<h5 id="control-and-regulation">Control and Regulation:</h5>
<h5 id="targeted-market-segment">Targeted Market Segment:</h5>
<h5 id="consumer-acceptance">Consumer Acceptance:</h5>
<h5 id="merchandising">Merchandising:</h5>
<h5 id="market-price">Market Price:</h5>
<h5 id="technological-significance">Technological Significance:</h5>
<p>The technological significance of the evaporator in a mechanical refrigeration system lies in its ability to evaporate liquid refrigerant (allowing it to absorb latent heat and thus perform useful cooling). In the public mind, however, the useful work was more simply that of cooling. </p>
<p>This lead astute manufactures to popularise the use of the term ‘cooling unit’ in place of evaporator. It was the term adopted by the industry in the early years, as it attempted to connect with the human experience of the times to better promote its wares, gaining market share in the embryonic years of Canada’s emerging consumer society. (See examples in early sale literature from the Kelvinator Co. of Canada) </p>
<p>Human experience and the social culture of the 1920’s also associated useful cooling with the melting of ice. Historically manufactures successfully played to this sense of public understanding by further marketing cooling units as icemakers. By this means they appealed to wide spread cultural understandings of how things got cooled, through the controlled melting of ice (the popular Canadian icebox of the 1920’s and 30’s). In a peculiar twist, it was often the job of the refrigeration sales or service man to explain to the homemaker that it was not really the ice in the ice cube trays that cooled the refrigerator, but the motor and compressor underneath. </p>
<p>In the 1920’s manufactures of mechanical refrigerators for the home appealed to the consumer public by promoting ice and ice cream as the new consumables, the new food sensations available for all those sufficiently affluent to enjoy the experience. Promotional literature focused on the pleasant sensation of ice cold beverages and on ice cream making at home ‘ using the latest cooling unit. A recipe and food life style book came with the refrigerator for the edification and instruction of the homemaker (See examples in early sale literature from the Kelvinator Co. of Canada). Ice and ice cream making in the home was, in fact, one of the significant, new ‘Gee whiz’, household technologies of the times. </p>
<p>This specimen is a particularly early, a well-preserved sample of cooling unit art form (Frigidaire shows this evaporator as discontinued May 5, 1928). Crude in manufacturing techniques, by subsequent standards, the industry would move quickly to modernise the look of its products and to develop the materials and manufacturing processes needed to produce them. (See for example items 011 and 012)</p>
<h5 id="industrial-significance">Industrial Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="socio-economic-significance">Socio-economic Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="socio-cultural-significance">Socio-cultural Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="donor">Donor:</h5>
<p>G. Leslie Oliver, The T. H. Oliver HVACR Collection</p>
<h5 id="hhcc-storage-location">HHCC Storage Location:</h5>
<h5 id="tracking">Tracking:</h5>
<h5 id="bibliographic-references">Bibliographic References:</h5>
<p>See Frigidaire Installation and Service Manual SER-405, for products before 1937, PP20-25</p>
<h5 id="notes">Notes:</h5>
<p>Note #1: Frigidaire shows this evaporator as discontinued May 5, 1928</p>
<h5 id="related-reports">Related Reports:</h5>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>2.01-7: Kelvinator 1935 Three Tray Cooling Unit for Cabinet Refrigerator</title>
        <author>
            <name>bo</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/2.01-7.html"/>
        <id>https://www.oliverassociates.ca/2.01-7.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/380/2.01-7.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="02.01: Household Evaporators"/>

        <updated>2023-05-15T14:11:34-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/380/2.01-7.jpg" alt="" />
                    HHCC Accession No. 2003.015 HHCC Classification Code: 2.01-7 Description: Three tray, dry evaporator for High-side float, in formed, rolled steel&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/380/2.01-7.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th><strong>HHCC Accession No. 2003.015</strong></th>
<th><strong>HHCC Classification Code:  2.01-7</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
</table>
<h5 id="description">Description:</h5>
<p>Three tray, dry evaporator for High-side float, in formed, rolled steel and heavy white porcelain, fast freezing shelf in stainless steel, for household cabinet refrigerator, Kelvinator, 1936.</p>
<hr>
<h5 id="group">Group:</h5>
<p>2.01 Refrigerating and Air Conditioning Evaporators - Household</p>
<h5 id="make">Make:</h5>
<p>Kelvinator</p>
<h5 id="manufacturer">Manufacturer:</h5>
<p>Klelvinator of Canada, London Ont.</p>
<h5 id="model">Model:</h5>
<h5 id="serial-no">Serial No.:</h5>
<h5 id="size">Size:</h5>
<p>5x 14x 14’h</p>
<h5 id="weight">Weight:</h5>
<p>18 lbs</p>
<h5 id="circa">Circa:</h5>
<p>1935</p>
<h5 id="rating">Rating:</h5>
<p>Rare snapshot in time, an example of a short-lived materials and construction technique, education, demonstration and research quality</p>
<h5 id="patent-datenumber">Patent Date/Number:</h5>
<h5 id="provenance">Provenance:</h5>
<p>From York County (York Region) Ontario, once a rich agricultural hinterlands, attracting early settlement in the last years of the 18th century. Located on the north slopes of the Oak Ridges Moraine, within 20 miles of Toronto, the County would also attract early ex-urban development, to be come a wealthy market place for the emerging household and consumer technologies of the early and mid 20th century. </p>
<p>This artifact was discovered in the 1950’s in the used stock of T. H. Oliver, Refrigeration and Electric Sales and Service, Aurora, Ontario, an early worker in the field of agricultural, commercial and consumer technology.</p>
<h5 id="type-and-design">Type and Design:</h5>
<p>Fabricated in formed and rolled steel sheet, to form refrigerant passages and twin suction line accumulators, this was an advanced design concept for the mid 1930’s It offered high heat transfer to meet new performance standards and consumer interests.</p>
<p>The stainless steel fast freezing shelf was ahead of its times, as well as being ahead of the manufacturing and materials know-how of the period. The cooling unit was subject to rapid deterioration due to corrosion, as this specimen illustrates.</p>
<h5 id="construction">Construction:</h5>
<h5 id="material">Material:</h5>
<h5 id="special-features">Special Features:</h5>
<h5 id="accessories">Accessories:</h5>
<h5 id="capacities">Capacities:</h5>
<h5 id="performance-characteristics">Performance Characteristics:</h5>
<h5 id="operation">Operation:</h5>
<h5 id="control-and-regulation">Control and Regulation:</h5>
<h5 id="targeted-market-segment">Targeted Market Segment:</h5>
<h5 id="consumer-acceptance">Consumer Acceptance:</h5>
<h5 id="merchandising">Merchandising:</h5>
<p>Kelvinator was anxious to promote the frozen food side of a growing consumer interest in new tastes and the conveniences of promoted by modernity. With a fast freezing, direct contact shelf, closed back and evaporator door (not included) this cooling unit was promoted as the gate way to the future (see Kelvinator promotional material of the period)</p>
<h5 id="market-price">Market Price:</h5>
<h5 id="technological-significance">Technological Significance:</h5>
<p>See Technological Significance documentation for THOC-HVACR 014. Like specimen 014, this historical artifact of the Canadian HVACR industry is a remarkable icon of its time, marking a dramatic change in engineering, manufacturing and styling, as the industry geared up to move well beyond its embryonic development years of the 1920’s.</p>
<h5 id="industrial-significance">Industrial Significance:</h5>
<p>The offering was a significant attempt by Kelvinator and the Canadian refrigeration industry to improve system, cooling and thermodynamic efficiencies, reduce manufacturing costs by investing in new materials, construction and manufacturing technologies, as well as to capture a second market interest in frozen foods.</p>
<h5 id="socio-economic-significance">Socio-economic Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="socio-cultural-significance">Socio-cultural Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="donor">Donor:</h5>
<p>G. Leslie Oliver, The T. H. Oliver HVACR Collection</p>
<h5 id="hhcc-storage-location">HHCC Storage Location:</h5>
<h5 id="tracking">Tracking:</h5>
<h5 id="bibliographic-references">Bibliographic References:</h5>
<h5 id="notes">Notes:</h5>
<h5 id="related-reports">Related Reports:</h5>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>1.03-2: Frigidaire 1926 Double Door, Cabinet Refrigerator</title>
        <author>
            <name>bo</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/1.03-2.html"/>
        <id>https://www.oliverassociates.ca/1.03-2.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/381/1.03-2.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="01.03: Commercial Refrigerating Equipment "/>

        <updated>2023-05-15T14:11:34-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/381/1.03-2.jpg" alt="" />
                    HHCC Accession No. 2003.009 HHCC Classification Code: 1.03-2 Description: Nine and One Half Cubic Foot, Double door, Cabinet Refrigerator, Frigidaire,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/381/1.03-2.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th><strong>HHCC Accession No. 2003.009</strong></th>
<th><strong>HHCC Classification Code:  1.03-2</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
</table>
<h5 id="description">Description:</h5>
<p>Nine and One Half Cubic Foot, Double door, Cabinet Refrigerator, Frigidaire, 1926</p>
<hr>
<details>
    <summary><b>Image Gallery (2 Images)</b></summary>
<div class="gallery gallery-wrapper--full"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="6">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/381/gallery/1.03-2.jpg" data-size="512x768"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/381/gallery/1.03-2-thumbnail.jpg" alt=""></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/381/gallery/1.03-2a.jpg" data-size="512x768"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/381/gallery/1.03-2a-thumbnail.jpg" alt=""></a></figure>
</div>
</details>

<h5 id="group">Group:</h5>
<p>1.03 Unitary Refrig and A/C Equipment and Systems - Commercial Refrigerating Equipment</p>
<h5 id="make">Make:</h5>
<p>Frigidaire</p>
<h5 id="manufacturer">Manufacturer:</h5>
<p>Frigidaire, Electric Refrigerator, Frigidaire Corp</p>
<h5 id="model">Model:</h5>
<p>Cabinet MP7</p>
<h5 id="serial-no">Serial No.:</h5>
<p>Condensing Unit 569038</p>
<h5 id="size">Size:</h5>
<p>34x 25x 58 1/2 “h</p>
<h5 id="weight">Weight:</h5>
<p>375 lbs</p>
<h5 id="circa">Circa:</h5>
<p>1926</p>
<h5 id="rating">Rating:</h5>
<p>Rare, Demonstration, Education and Research Quality</p>
<h5 id="patent-datenumber">Patent Date/Number:</h5>
<h5 id="provenance">Provenance:</h5>
<p>From York County (York Region) Ontario, once a rich agricultural hinterlands, attracting early settlement in the last years of the 18th century. Located on the north slopes of the Oak Ridges Moraine, within 20 miles of Toronto, the County would also attract early ex-urban development, to be come a wealthy market place for the emerging household and consumer technologies of the early and mid 20th century. 
This artifact was discovered in the 1950’s in the used stock of T. H. Oliver, Refrigeration and Electric Sales and Service, Aurora, Ontario, an early worker in the field of agricultural, industrial and consumer technology.</p>
<h5 id="type-and-design">Type and Design:</h5>
<p>Unitary design and construction with insulated refrigerated cabinet, evaporator and expansion valve, and self-contained refrigerant condensing unit, electric motor driven. Operating system - compression refrigeration type, theoretical Carnot cycle
Self-contained condensing unit with belts driven, 2 cylinder compressor, single-phase electric motor, and air-cooled condenser.</p>
<h5 id="construction">Construction:</h5>
<p>Frigidaire cabinet Model MP7, two door refrigerated compartment, with original white Dulux finished exterior, galvanised steel panels, now chipping and worn, applied to heavy wooden cabinet frame with aluminum corner trim strips. </p>
<p>Porcelain steel interior finish, with original tinned wire mesh shelving; wooden framed doors and breaker strips in white Dulux enamel. </p>
<p>Large, self-contained, lower, two door, ventilated machine compartment, Original hardware throughout. </p>
<p>Frigidaire Condensing Unit Serial 569038; twin cylinder compressor Model S, 1 1/4’’ bore x 1 3/4’’ stroke, 350 rpm, 12’’ fly wheel, V belt drive; 1/2’ oval wound, stack, copper tube condenser, for convection air cooling (with non-finned surface); </p>
<p>Low pressure ‘cold control switch’, copper/bronze ‘sylphon’ (bellows), calm operated (See THOC Ref. 2.2, Compressors, P. 23). </p>
<p>11.5 lb. refrigerant receiver for sulphur dioxide; 1/4 HP 25 cycle motor replaced by 60 cycle in 1948 at the time of Hydro conversion in Ontario at which time the machine was still in active service. (See Ref. 2.1, Ch. 1A, P. 3)</p>
<p>Frigidaire low side float, brass, three tray, ice-making, flooded coil evaporator, Model 6, fully shrouded with unique ‘stove pipe’ hole and removable plug on bottom for humidity control. Copper distributing tubes with non-finned surfaces. Tin plated evaporator surfaces with chrome plated front panels and shroud in Dulux coated galvanized steel. Five and a half lb. ice making capacity. Evaporator discontinued by Frigidaire, Dec. 26, 1928. (See THOC Ref. 2.1, Ch 1A)</p>
<h5 id="material">Material:</h5>
<p>The wooden frame construction and metal sheathing panels stand as a fine example of fabrication and construction methods in a period, prior to the advent of more cost effective welded steel frames and sophisticated brake-formed metal panel techniques of the 1930’s. The size and weight of the self-contained, steel framed condensing unit with slow speed, two cylinder compressor and open, belt drive represents the end of a generation of such machines in the kitchens of the Nation. Their weight, size and noise would shortly be all greatly reduced with the introduction of smaller, quieter hermetically sealed refrigeration systems. </p>
<p>The use of noxious refrigerants would also soon disappear, giving the electric refrigerator a greatly improved public image among Canadian householders. The heat transfer surfaces employed here by Frigidaire are unique to the period. For both condenser and evaporator surfaces the manufacturer has not made use of any secondary heat transfer surfaces, neither in the form of plates nor fins. </p>
<p>The results, in both instances, are relatively inefficient extended primary surfaces, which add considerably to the bulk and weight of the refrigerator. The introduction of more efficient heat transfer surface materials and fabrication techniques would shortly contribute to smaller more efficient refrigeration systems for household use.</p>
<h5 id="special-features">Special Features:</h5>
<h5 id="accessories">Accessories:</h5>
<p>:</p>
<h5 id="capacities">Capacities:</h5>
<h5 id="performance-characteristics">Performance Characteristics:</h5>
<h5 id="operation">Operation:</h5>
<h5 id="control-and-regulation">Control and Regulation:</h5>
<h5 id="targeted-market-segment">Targeted Market Segment:</h5>
<p>The refrigerator stands as an icon of upper class social distinction, tastes and the life styles of the 1920’s in Canada. It was widely promoted in the elite media of the day, targeting the owners of the grand Victorian and Edwardian homes of the period. (See also Item 007 above) </p>
<p>In an advertisement appearing in the April 1926 National Geographic, a maid in full uniform is seen at the fully loaded open refrigerator in a commodious kitchen of the times. Here the promotion was in the form of an appeal to a new modernity, one in which modern kitchen planning became an important sales lever.</p>
<h5 id="consumer-acceptance">Consumer Acceptance:</h5>
<h5 id="merchandising">Merchandising:</h5>
<h5 id="market-price">Market Price:</h5>
<h5 id="technological-significance">Technological Significance:</h5>
<p>Unitary Refrigeration Equipment: The idea of a unitary piece of refrigeration or air conditioning equipment was a significant one in its own right, one that had to wait its time. The scientists, engineers and inventors in the early years of the 20th century were intrigued and obsessed with the power of the technology and of its possible market potential. What they saw was the newly discovered principles of physics and heat engines - following, for example, the early works of Carnot, Faraday, Kelvin, and the later work of Perkins, Larsen and Carrier, to name a few. </p>
<p>They understood the promise of the technology for the public good, not to say its consumer sales potential. Early engineering work advanced on a multiple fronts with development of compressors, heat exchangers, valves and piping variously strung together in configurations that would be found to work, but only after much experimentation.</p>
<p>The arrival of unitary equipment, all those parts organised into a single whole, a single unit of construction, a ‘black box’, that could be offered to the consumer market was a significant technological and cultural event. Technologically the refrigerator would need to be seen to be safe, reliable, maintainable and useful. As well, in order to attract the development capital needed, it must be seen as potentially saleable and affordable, contributing to life’s needs and desires. Its socio- cultural and economic significance was marked, for it would change much. As Canadians we would quickly come enjoy potentially healthier lives, expect new levels of comfort and convenience, with a broader, safer, more diverse and enjoyable diet. </p>
<p>As a result, Canadians would quickly come to think of their day differently, for the day would be defined and punctuated in different ways than ever before, as a result of the introduction of modern, electric, household appliances, of which refrigerators, freezers and room air conditioners would be a central part, by the mid 20th century </p>
<p>J. M Larsen produced a manually operated household refrigerator of sorts in 1913, but it was not until 1918 that the Kelvinator Company marketed the first automatic, unitary refrigerator for the home. In that year, it is reported to have sold sixty-seven machines. (See Note 1) The historic artifacts in Group 1.00, Unitary Equipment, including significant samplings the early work of Kelvinator of Canada, provide a rare view of the evolution of unitary refrigeration and air conditioning applications, as they evolved in Canada in the first half of the 20th century. </p>
<p>For those formative years, the artifacts in this Group, 1.00, are typical of the offerings of the Canadian refrigeration and air conditioning industry. They personified the applications found in the homes, farms and commercial premises of the period for, those that could afford life’s new amenities of comfort, convenience and privilege. </p>
<p>This Specimen, along with inventory item  No.008 help to profile the significant changes in the industry’s public offerings over a brief 2 years, from 1926 to 1928. The last half of the decade was a period remarkable styling, engineering and manufacturing innovation in the industry, inspired by the rapid market growth of the period. Included, as highlighted in contrasting the two specimens, are styling [square to round, modern corners of the Art deco], finish [yellowing paint to gleaming white porcelain], size and weight of condensing unit.</p>
<h5 id="industrial-significance">Industrial Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="socio-economic-significance">Socio-economic Significance:</h5>
<p>This specimen stands as a cultural icon of upper class social distinction, tastes and the life styles of the 1920’s in Canada. It was widely promoted in the elite media of the day, targeting the owners of the grand Victorian and Edwardian homes of the period. In an advertisement appearing in the April 1926 National Geographic, a maid in full uniform is seen at the fully loaded open refrigerator in a commodious kitchen of the times. Here the promotion was in the form of an appeal to a new modernity, one in which modern kitchen planning became an important sales lever.</p>
<h5 id="socio-cultural-significance">Socio-cultural Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="donor">Donor:</h5>
<p>G. Leslie Oliver, The T. H. Oliver HVACR Collection</p>
<h5 id="hhcc-storage-location">HHCC Storage Location:</h5>
<h5 id="tracking">Tracking:</h5>
<h5 id="bibliographic-references">Bibliographic References:</h5>
<p>See THOC Ref. 2.1, Ch. 1A, P. 32
See Frigidaire Manuals</p>
<h5 id="notes">Notes:</h5>
<h5 id="related-reports">Related Reports:</h5>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>2.01-8: Kelvinator 1936 Four Tray Cooling Unit for Cabinet Refrigerator</title>
        <author>
            <name>bo</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/2.01-8.html"/>
        <id>https://www.oliverassociates.ca/2.01-8.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/382/2.01-8.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="02.01: Household Evaporators"/>

        <updated>2023-05-15T14:11:34-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/382/2.01-8.jpg" alt="" />
                    HHCC Accession No. 2003.016 HHCC Classification Code: 2.01-8 Description: Horizontal, four tray, dry evaporator for high-side float, in formed, rolled&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/382/2.01-8.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th><strong>HHCC Accession No. 2003.016</strong></th>
<th><strong>HHCC Classification Code:  2.01-8</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
</table>
<h5 id="description">Description:</h5>
<p>Horizontal, four tray, dry evaporator for high-side float, in formed, rolled steel and heavy white porcelain, with fast freezing shelf in stainless steel, ‘high tech’ remote bulb temperature control, defrost and overload controllers, for use on household cabinet refrigerator, Kelvinator, 1936.</p>
<hr>
<h5 id="group">Group:</h5>
<p>2.01 Refrigerating and Air Conditioning Evaporators - Household</p>
<h5 id="make">Make:</h5>
<p>Kelvinator</p>
<h5 id="manufacturer">Manufacturer:</h5>
<p>Kelvinator of Canada, London Ont.</p>
<h5 id="model">Model:</h5>
<h5 id="serial-no">Serial No.:</h5>
<h5 id="size">Size:</h5>
<p>12x 15x 8’h</p>
<h5 id="weight">Weight:</h5>
<p>20 lbs</p>
<h5 id="circa">Circa:</h5>
<p>1936</p>
<h5 id="rating">Rating:</h5>
<p>Exhibit, education, demonstration and research quality. A rare piece of refrigerating hardware, demonstrating the advancemences made in refrigerating engineering, automation and regulation by the mid 1930’s. Also exemplifying the work of a new breed of industrial workers, the industrial designer, of the period.</p>
<h5 id="patent-datenumber">Patent Date/Number:</h5>
<h5 id="provenance">Provenance:</h5>
<p>From York County (York Region) Ontario, once a rich agricultural hinterlands, attracting early settlement in the last years of the 18th century. Located on the north slopes of the Oak Ridges Moraine, within 20 miles of Toronto, the County would also attract early ex-urban development, to be come a wealthy market place for the emerging household and consumer technologies of the early and mid 20th century. </p>
<p>This artifact was discovered in the 1950’s in the used stock of T. H. Oliver, Refrigeration and Electric Sales and Service, Aurora, Ontario, an early worker in the field of agricultural, commercial and consumer technology.</p>
<h5 id="type-and-design">Type and Design:</h5>
<p>Similar to previous item, 015, this cooling unit is fabricated in formed and rolled steel sheet, to form refrigerant passages, with twin suction line accumulators, An advanced design concept for the mid 1930’s, it offered high heat transfer to meet new performance standards and new found consumer interests of the time. The movement to more integrated and smoothly articulated functional units (evaporators), made up of multiple, individual component parts, each with a life and purpose of its own, is evident.  </p>
<p>The stainless steel fast freezing shelf was ahead of its times, as well as being ahead of the manufacturing and materials know-how of the period. The cooling unit was subject to rapid deterioration due to corrosion of dissimilarmaterials, as this specimen illustrates. </p>
<p>What is new here, however, is also the horizontal pattern adopted by the coling unit, for central mounting on the top of the refrigerator (See picture from original manufacturers literature appended). The trend to larger cooling units, accommodating the consumer’s interest in frozen foods, was about to significantly alter the way cooling units (evaporators) would be configured in the future. </p>
<p>The cooling unit would grow in size, spreading across the top of the refrigerator, until it occupied the full width of the cabinet and then move downwards to take over an ever increasing percentage of the refrigerated space.</p>
<h5 id="construction">Construction:</h5>
<p>A significant aspect of the movement to more integrated and smoothly articulated engineering component design, is coming to see fully functioning components more holistically. Here the cooling unit, originally conceived as a box for ice cubes, with coils of copper tubing wrapped around it, has been re-conceptualised as a single operating entity. Box and coil are now one.</p>
<h5 id="material">Material:</h5>
<h5 id="special-features">Special Features:</h5>
<p>Gleaming white porcelain finish; full back cooling unit with door in brushed aluminium ( a new designer material of the mid 30’s) with a classic design idiom.</p>
<h5 id="accessories">Accessories:</h5>
<p>: 
Ranco remote bulb temperature control, with automatic defrosts switch and manual reset motor overload protector- revolutionary for the times.</p>
<p>Suction line check valve for high-side float operation. An operating system which itself would be short lived, but one that would be a significant step on the road to increasingly reliable, maintainable, thermodynamically efficient and affordable refrigerating systems for the Canadian household   </p>
<p>Inverted flare-tubing connectors, a system developed in the early 30’s, a concept that would be short lived. The system was designed to reduce the bulk of refrigerant tubing connectors and improve the reliability of refrigerant piping.  </p>
<p>Note the natural rubber mounting grommets in designer white, an appeal to a new style conscious public, as the household refrigerator was moved up the social ladder.</p>
<h5 id="capacities">Capacities:</h5>
<h5 id="performance-characteristics">Performance Characteristics:</h5>
<p>The effects of corrosion on the suction line header, resulting from the porcelain on steel construction is evident, leading often to premature failure.</p>
<h5 id="operation">Operation:</h5>
<h5 id="control-and-regulation">Control and Regulation:</h5>
<h5 id="targeted-market-segment">Targeted Market Segment:</h5>
<h5 id="consumer-acceptance">Consumer Acceptance:</h5>
<h5 id="merchandising">Merchandising:</h5>
<h5 id="market-price">Market Price:</h5>
<h5 id="technological-significance">Technological Significance:</h5>
<p>See Technological Significance documentation for THOC-HVACR 014 and 015. Like specimens 014 and 015, this historical artifact of the Canadian HVACR industry is a remarkable icon of its time, marking a dramatic change in engineering, concepts, manufacturing and styling, as the industry geared up to move well beyond its embryonic development years of the 1920’s. </p>
<p>Of special note is the level of automation and refrigeration system regulation reflected here, in remote bulb temperature controlling, defrost control and motor over load protection (See also historical artifacts THOC-HVACR Group 7.00 ). Seen here are the early manifestations of engineering thought in the practical application of what would become the cybernetic revolution of the 40’s and 50’s, in which mechanical and electrical systems were conceived as purposeful, self-regulating and self-directing entities.</p>
<p>Here, too, the unprepared public would be faced, most for the first time, with a myriad of switches and buttons (three), arrayed on a control panel (not included), which they were expected to understand and use effectively ‘ most did not. The local refrigeration salesman and serviceman, the support network of the times, were constantly on call, if  the householder found melted ice-cream, and other dripping contents on opening the refrigerator.</p>
<p>Here, then, are the early manifestations, realised in the engineering concepts and hardware of the period, of the on-coming revolution in the processing of meaningful, purposeful, information through feedback loops. (See ‘Modern Systems Research for the Behavioral Scientist, W. Buckley, 1968)         .</p>
<h5 id="industrial-significance">Industrial Significance:</h5>
<p>This offering was a significant attempt by Kelvinator and the Canadian refrigeration industry to improve system cooling and thermodynamic efficiencies, reduce manufacturing costs and progressively automate and regulate their systems better. The industry was investing heavily in new materials, construction and manufacturing technologies, in order to capture the interests of a second market buyers market.</p>
<h5 id="socio-economic-significance">Socio-economic Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="socio-cultural-significance">Socio-cultural Significance:</h5>
<p>The trend to the ‘gentrification’ of the refrigerator and the kitchens of the nation was on its way, with the appeal to a new generation of urban design tastes, as reflected for example in the cooling unit’s designer door. The trend to gentrification would role on, unabated to the end of the century and beyond.</p>
<h5 id="donor">Donor:</h5>
<p>G. Leslie Oliver, The T. H. Oliver HVACR Collection</p>
<h5 id="hhcc-storage-location">HHCC Storage Location:</h5>
<h5 id="tracking">Tracking:</h5>
<h5 id="bibliographic-references">Bibliographic References:</h5>
<h5 id="notes">Notes:</h5>
<h5 id="related-reports">Related Reports:</h5>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>2.01-10: 1940 Household Refrigerator Cooling Unit</title>
        <author>
            <name>bo</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/2.01-10.html"/>
        <id>https://www.oliverassociates.ca/2.01-10.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/383/2.01-10.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="02.01: Household Evaporators"/>

        <updated>2023-05-15T14:11:34-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/383/2.01-10.jpg" alt="" />
                    HHCC Accession No. 2003.018 HHCC Classification Code: 2.01-10 Description: The Canadian refrigeration industry was moving beyond the concept of a&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/383/2.01-10.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th><strong>HHCC Accession No. 2003.018</strong></th>
<th><strong>HHCC Classification Code:  2.01-10</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
</table>
<h5 id="description">Description:</h5>
<p>The Canadian refrigeration industry was moving beyond the concept of a refrigerant evaporator as ‘ice maker’ (see item 011), to a cooling unit designed for frozen foods. Using advanced materials engineering for the period, this specimen is fabricated in stainless steel, with high conductivity, rolled and formed refrigerant passages and equipped with an automatic expansion valve, 1940.</p>
<hr>
<h5 id="group">Group:</h5>
<p>2.01 Refrigerating and Air Conditioning Evaporators - Household</p>
<h5 id="make">Make:</h5>
<p>Unknown, possibly Kelvinator</p>
<h5 id="manufacturer">Manufacturer:</h5>
<p>Unknown, possibly Kelvinator of Canada, London Ont.</p>
<h5 id="model">Model:</h5>
<h5 id="serial-no">Serial No.:</h5>
<h5 id="size">Size:</h5>
<p>11x 11x 11’h</p>
<h5 id="weight">Weight:</h5>
<p>11 lbs</p>
<h5 id="circa">Circa:</h5>
<p>1940</p>
<h5 id="rating">Rating:</h5>
<p>Exhibit, demonstration, education and research quality</p>
<h5 id="patent-datenumber">Patent Date/Number:</h5>
<h5 id="provenance">Provenance:</h5>
<p>From York County (York Region) Ontario, once a rich agricultural hinterlands, attracting early settlement in the last years of the 18th century. Located on the north slopes of the Oak Ridges Moraine, within 20 miles of Toronto, the County would also attract early ex-urban development, to be come a wealthy market place for the emerging household and consumer technologies of the early and mid 20th century. </p>
<p>This artifact was discovered in the 1950’s in the used stock of T. H. Oliver, Refrigeration and Electric Sales and Service, Aurora, Ontario, an early worker in the field of agricultural, commercial and consumer technology.</p>
<h5 id="type-and-design">Type and Design:</h5>
<p>The Canadian refrigeration industry was moving beyond the troublesome fabrication of refrigerant evaporators in formed and rolled steel sheet, in order to form refrigerant passages. Here high conductivity stainless steel was used. It offered high heat transfer to meet new performance standards and consumer interests in larger cooling units to accommodate packaged frozen foods now appearing in some areas.</p>
<h5 id="construction">Construction:</h5>
<h5 id="material">Material:</h5>
<h5 id="special-features">Special Features:</h5>
<p>Built in mechanical lifters to release ice cube trays and frozen food packages</p>
<h5 id="accessories">Accessories:</h5>
<p>Detroit Lubricator automatic expansion valve Model #672, Serial 1959314</p>
<h5 id="capacities">Capacities:</h5>
<h5 id="performance-characteristics">Performance Characteristics:</h5>
<h5 id="operation">Operation:</h5>
<h5 id="control-and-regulation">Control and Regulation:</h5>
<h5 id="targeted-market-segment">Targeted Market Segment:</h5>
<h5 id="consumer-acceptance">Consumer Acceptance:</h5>
<h5 id="merchandising">Merchandising:</h5>
<h5 id="market-price">Market Price:</h5>
<h5 id="technological-significance">Technological Significance:</h5>
<p>The industry was moving rapidly to more thermodynamically and mechanically efficient refrigerating systems, with the development of non-noxious, refrigerants, and hermetically sealed refrigeration systems and a new generation of smaller less trouble prone flow controls ‘ represented here by the automatic expansion valve (See artifact Group 3.00) .</p>
<h5 id="industrial-significance">Industrial Significance:</h5>
<p>The Canadian refrigeration industry was continuing to invest heavily in new materials and manufacturing technology to meet the market potential of the period. Much of the design and engineering development of the time was both facilitated and accelerated by the  research of wartime years, as well as being constrained by the shortages of materials and skilled labour.</p>
<h5 id="socio-economic-significance">Socio-economic Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="socio-cultural-significance">Socio-cultural Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="donor">Donor:</h5>
<p>G. Leslie Oliver, The T. H. Oliver HVACR Collection</p>
<h5 id="hhcc-storage-location">HHCC Storage Location:</h5>
<h5 id="tracking">Tracking:</h5>
<h5 id="bibliographic-references">Bibliographic References:</h5>
<h5 id="notes">Notes:</h5>
<h5 id="related-reports">Related Reports:</h5>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>2.01-13: Air Coils 1946 Two Tray Cooling Unit for Household Refrigerator</title>
        <author>
            <name>bo</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/2.01-13.html"/>
        <id>https://www.oliverassociates.ca/2.01-13.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/384/2.01-13.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="02.01: Household Evaporators"/>

        <updated>2023-05-15T14:11:34-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/384/2.01-13.jpg" alt="" />
                    HHCC Accession No. 2003.020 HHCC Classification Code: 2.01-13 Description: A general replacement, 2 tray cooling unit for household refrigerator. A&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.oliverassociates.ca/media/posts/384/2.01-13.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th><strong>HHCC Accession No. 2003.020</strong></th>
<th><strong>HHCC Classification Code:  2.01-13</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
</table>
<h5 id="description">Description:</h5>
<p>A general replacement, 2 tray cooling unit for household refrigerator. A transition evaporator technology; fabricated in aluminium, using coiled, tinned copper tubing, sandwiched between aluminium plates;. equipped with Ranco type KW remote bulb temperature control, Air Coils Oakville Ont. 1946</p>
<hr>
<h5 id="group">Group:</h5>
<p>2.01 Refrigerating and Air Conditioning Evaporators - Household</p>
<h5 id="make">Make:</h5>
<p>Air Coils</p>
<h5 id="manufacturer">Manufacturer:</h5>
<p>Air Coils, Oakville Ont.</p>
<h5 id="model">Model:</h5>
<p>31-17</p>
<h5 id="serial-no">Serial No.:</h5>
<h5 id="size">Size:</h5>
<p>10x 12x 9’h</p>
<h5 id="weight">Weight:</h5>
<p>8 lbs</p>
<h5 id="circa">Circa:</h5>
<p>1946</p>
<h5 id="rating">Rating:</h5>
<p>New and unused, exhibit, demonstration, education and research quality</p>
<h5 id="patent-datenumber">Patent Date/Number:</h5>
<h5 id="provenance">Provenance:</h5>
<p>From York County (York Region) Ontario, once a rich agricultural hinterlands, attracting early settlement in the last years of the 18th century. Located on the north slopes of the Oak Ridges Moraine, within 20 miles of Toronto, the County would also attract early ex-urban development, to be come a wealthy market place for the emerging household and consumer technologies of the early and mid 20th century. </p>
<p>This artifact was discovered in the 1950’s in the used stock of T. H. Oliver, Refrigeration and Electric Sales and Service, Aurora, Ontario, an early worker in the field of agricultural, commercial and consumer technology.</p>
<h5 id="type-and-design">Type and Design:</h5>
<p>The evaporator was engineered by Air Coils for the general replacement market of the post World War II years. Full equipped and loaded with features for the period, it included the latest remote bulb tempertaure control technology of the times. </p>
<p>It employs an early engineering approach to aluminium evaporator construction. Coiled copper tubing is sandwiched between high conductivity aluminium plates to form the top, bottom and shelf of this 2 tray, ice making, evaporator. The cabinet is of formed and riveted in aluminium sheet stock with 1” fins at 1” centres on the two sidewalls.</p>
<h5 id="construction">Construction:</h5>
<p>This simple approach to fabrication set aside, for the moment, the major problem to be overcome in the engineering of aluminium evaporators. The challenge was to develop robust bonding techniques required for pressure tight connections between copper and aluminium. In 1946 these techniques were yet to be perfected. The repair of leaks in aluminium evaporators would remain a challenge for the industry. The early aluminium stock was also soft and easily punctured.</p>
<h5 id="material">Material:</h5>
<h5 id="special-features">Special Features:</h5>
<h5 id="accessories">Accessories:</h5>
<h5 id="capacities">Capacities:</h5>
<h5 id="performance-characteristics">Performance Characteristics:</h5>
<h5 id="operation">Operation:</h5>
<h5 id="control-and-regulation">Control and Regulation:</h5>
<h5 id="targeted-market-segment">Targeted Market Segment:</h5>
<p>The replacement market of the post World War II years was substantial. Not only due to the scarcities of wartime, but also the significant improvements in technology, and the Canadian consumer’s desire to modernise.</p>
<h5 id="consumer-acceptance">Consumer Acceptance:</h5>
<h5 id="merchandising">Merchandising:</h5>
<h5 id="market-price">Market Price:</h5>
<h5 id="technological-significance">Technological Significance:</h5>
<p>The significance of this specimen, like 019, rests in its evolutionary context. It is part of the dynamic, rapidly changing pattern of developmental events that saw the Canadian refrigeration industry move beyond its crude, early offerings to the households of the nation and do so in a period of much less than two decades.  </p>
<p>Of special significance, technologically, is the dramatic tansition from the  crude designs of the 1920’s and 30’sto those of the 40’s enabled by new materials science and newly informed engineering theory and practice.    .</p>
<h5 id="industrial-significance">Industrial Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="socio-economic-significance">Socio-economic Significance:</h5>
<h5 id="socio-cultural-significance">Socio-cultural Significance:</h5>
<p>What is dramatised, here, is the social and cultural commitment of the period to up-grade, repair and maintain, rather than replace. While a function of the supply market of the day,  more importantly the behaviour pattern reflected the core, prevailing value system of Canadians - their respect for thrift and getting by. These core values would, however,  change dramatically over the next decade, as a result Canada’s consumer society about burst on the scene with explosive force.  .</p>
<h5 id="donor">Donor:</h5>
<p>G. Leslie Oliver, The T. H. Oliver HVACR Collection</p>
<h5 id="hhcc-storage-location">HHCC Storage Location:</h5>
<h5 id="tracking">Tracking:</h5>
<h5 id="bibliographic-references">Bibliographic References:</h5>
<h5 id="notes">Notes:</h5>
<h5 id="related-reports">Related Reports:</h5>
<p>Exhibition Catalogue for CMX02 show, March 2002</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
